Guide to the Katharine Vaughn Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Katherine Vaughn Papers
1920-1930
RG 31
Yale University Divinity School Library
2.5
(4 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, collected material and photographs document the work of Katherine Vaughn with the YWCA in Canton and Shanghai, China from 1920-1930.
Vaughn, Katherine
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Vaughn, 2008
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Katherine Vaughn was born in Brooklyn, NY on January 31, 1888. She graduated from Packer Collegiate Institute and Vassar College. For several years she was on the staff of Pratt Institute in Brooklyn. From 1920 to 1948, she was associated with the YWCA, serving for eight years as general secretary in Canton and Shanghai, China. Later she was head of publications and booksales for the YWCA in New York. She joined the staff of Fifth Avenue Presbyterian Church in 1948 and worked there until her death.
Scope and Contents
Detailed correspondence provides valuable documentation of Vaughn's work with the YWCA in China. Her professional work, social life, and her observations of political events shed light on the life of a single woman missionary in China during the 1920s. Complementary documentation may be found in the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records in the Sophia Smith Collection at Smith College.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1290-1930
II. Writings, 1920
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1920-1930, n.d.
Missions -- China; Young Women's Christian associations -- China; Missionaries; Vaughn, Katherine
- Correspondence, 1920-1930; Series I
  - To Family
    - Enroute and arrival in China, 1920 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - In Canton, 1920 Oct (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Regarding everday life, 1920 Nov-1921 Jun (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
    - Including regarding camping vacation, 1921 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Including regarding visit from Rockefellers, 1921 Sep -1922 Feb (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - At National Christian Conference in Shanghai, 1922 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - In Hong Kong and Canton, 1922 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - On vacation in Typhoon, 1922 Jul-Aug (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - In Canton, 1922 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    - Including regarding visits to Hong Kong, 1923 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Including regarding co-worker marrying, 1923 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Including regarding camping in Hong Kong and bad storm, 1923 Jul-Sep (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - To Shanghai for conference, 1923 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - In Canton, 1924 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Visit to Hong Kong and planning conference, 1924 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Visiting Hong Kong, 1924 Jul-Sep (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - In Canton; civil war; looting, 1924 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - To Shanghai and return to U.S., 1925 Jan-Mar (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Return to Canton, China, 1926 Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - In Canton, 1927 Jan-Feb (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Evacuated to Hong Kong: war, 1927 Mar-Apr (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - In Canton, 1927 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Visiting Hong Kong: Canton, 1927 Jul-Oct (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
    - In Canton: Hong Kong, 1927 Nov-1928 Apr (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
    - Move to Shanghai, 1928 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Convention/ visit to Peking, 1928 Jul-Aug (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - In Shanghai, 1928 Sep-1929 Apr (Box 2, Folder 36-38)
    - Including regarding political unrest, 1929 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Vacationn in H.K.; Shanghai; Conference, 1929 Jul-Sep (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - In Shanghai, 1929 Oct-1930 Apr (Box 2, Folder 41-43)
    - In Shanghai: political unrest, 1930 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Return to U.S., 1930 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Letters to/ from others
    - B-E (Box 3, Folder 46)
      Scope and Contents
      Including: Bond, Brown, Chin, Clark, Denstoe, Edwinson
    - H-P (Box 3, Folder 47)
      Including: Helen T, Howson, Hsai, Kirk, Lin, Liu, Mil, Paget, Parker
    - R-W (Box 3, Folder 48)
      Including: Rosalee, Shibrya, Shui, Spiedel, Tsit, Willis, Wu
  - Circular letters of Katherine Vaughn
    - Reports from Shanghai, 1928, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Letters of others
    - Mr. and Mrs. George Vaughn, 1926-1927 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - To Mrs. George Vaughn from Katharine's friend, 1923-1930 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Henry Hodgkins, Maud Russell, Ma King Kwang, T.Z. Koo (National Comm. reports), 1927-1930 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Writings, 1922
  - "Homemaking in Canton", "Canton 1922" (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Personal items and memorabilia, 1920-1930, n.d.
  - Biographical Information
    - Photo; Funeral service; Research paper: "Katherine Vaughn, Missionary in China" by David Vaughn (grand-nephew) (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Passport and documents (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Collected items
    - Cards, programs, travels (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - News clippings regarding China (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Booklets, YWCA Newsletters (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Photograph album to China scenery, groups, 1920-1922 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Photo album, 1922 Dec-1926 Sep (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Photo album; Canton and Shanghai, 1926-1930 (Box 4, Folder 61)